Register of the Daniel Lerner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Captured German Documents, 1944-1945 (Boxes 1-9)
  - DE-File (Folder 1: 3)
    - Guderian's proclamation to soldiers on the Eastern front (#269) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Education of the young in Nazi Germany today (#271)
    - "Richtmänner" (#272)
    - Three hundred and forty Volksgrenadier Div. NSFO confidential directives of February 14 (#273)
    - The Party comes in for criticism. Four extracts from German civilian letters (#274)
    - Students' Order of the Day to commemorate the day Hitler came to power (#276)
    - Verpflichtungserklärungen used in the German Army (#277)
    - Conscription of medical students (#278)
    - Ten extracts from German soldiers' letters (#279)
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians (#280)
    - uniforms (#281), 1945
    - How the evacuation of Germans from Romania, Yugoslavia, Hungary, and Slovakia was carried out (#282)
    - The last COMB-OUT (#283)
    - Sniping, training, and use of snipers to be intensified (#284)
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German civilians in (#285), January 1945
    - Change of regulations re soldiers from annexed and German administered territory (#286)
    - "Soldaten der Ostfront" (Guderian on enemy propaganda to the troops) (#287)
    - German propaganda to German troops (#288)
    - Forged order to the Allies from 89 I.D. (#290)
    - Himmler takes a hand as C-in-C Oberrhein (#291)
    - The hold of the Catholic Church on German women. Extracts from SD report (#292)
    - The influence of the film on German Youth (#293)
    - Grohe's desperate call for hatred and resistance (#294)
    - Police raids against foreign workers (#295)
    - SS-man's views about a Waffen-SS battalion commander (#296)
    - NSFO directives re anti-Russian atrocity propaganda (#297)
    - Volume of faked orders and false passes in the Wehrmacht seriously affecting conduct of war (#298)
    - Combatant status for party officials (#299)
    - Blaskowitz order, 5 March (#301) (Folder 2: 5)
    - East contribution, (#302), February 1945
    - What price rubber? (#303)
    - Rundstedt's Order of the Day, (#304), 11 February 1945
    - Use of the Volkssturm in Division rear areas (#305)
    - The position of miners in evacuated areas (#306)
    - Reprisals on SS-Deserters' kith and kin (#307)
    - Letters written by soldiers of the Lorient garrison. Extracts (#308)
    - "Planned evacuation" of transport workers from the West? (#309)
    - Himmler fights anti-Nazi youth cliques (#310)
    - The case against the SS as presented to their own recruits (#311)
    - Regulations re handling of POWs (#312)
    - Bormann decree re Party influence in jurisdiction (#313)
    - Strength through fear. NSFO not sure about morale-building effect of calculated intimidation - but military situation leaves no choice (#314)
    - Workers' meals poor, insufficient, and costly (#315)
    - Police forces to stay behind in evacuated areas (#316)
    - Himmler's verdict on the Allies (#317)
    - Shaded propaganda. Special treatment of colored POWs (#318)
    - Disused mine galleries provide hideout for soldiers, Ostarbeiter, and civilians (#319)
    - Himmler's order re execution of Salisch and Hassenstein for cowardice (#320)
    - Two kinds of evacuations (#321)
    - "Sippenhaft" rejected by soldiers (#322)
    - Civilians suffer for lack of discipline among troops (#323)
    - Foreigners and the Volkssturm (#324)
    - Security measures re soldiers recalled from armament factories (#325)
    - Volkssturm "dress rehearsal" falls flat (#326)
    - Air raids and censorship (#327)
    - "It is senseless to continue this war." Public opinion survey (#328)
    - "Only fatheads believe we will lose the war" (#329)
    - Fear of foreign workers rising (#330)
    - Gangsters and murderers. Two-front war in atrocity propaganda (#331)
    - Railway officials failing in their duties (#332) (Folder 2: 6)
    - The bottom of the barrel (#333)
    - Twelve commandments of spiritual warfare (#334)
    - Foreigners - all sorts (#335)
    - SS-Jagdverbände call for volunteers with banking experience (#336)
    - Göring speaks his mind. Drastic measures to be taken against Luftwaffe personnel to stop rot in morale (#337)
    - Reserved for Generals! (#338)
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German civilians (#339)
    - Protection of large families - an empty phrase! (#340)
    - Rundstedt knew: No war without railways (#341)
    - Flight from the Rhine. Extract from typical letter (#342)
    - Failure of German propaganda (#343)
    - Rumors preceding Allied troops (#344)
    - Bormann on Party discipline (#345)
    - News Service - Nazi style (#346)
    - POWs treated like convicts (#347)
    - Extensive looting by Party (#348)
    - Double deferment (#349)
    - Death sentences to preserve quality of the Nation (#350)
    - Test of anti-Semitism (#351)
    - "Dienst bis zum Umfallen" (#352)
    - Analysis of captured German civilian letters (#353)
    - Ecclesiastical letter from Cardinal Faulhaber, (#354), 15 November 1944
    - Wehrwolf recruiting (#355)
    - Penalty for insulting the Volkssturm (#356)
    - Encircled troops, fortresses, and other isolated units (#357)
    - "We surrender!" Extracts from letters written by German civilians (#358)
    - Hitler's armament production emergency program (#359)
    - Formation of the "Freicorps Adolf Hitler" (#360) (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Hitler's Scorched Earth Order of 19 March (#361)
    - Himmler ordered compulsory evacuation of clergymen (#362)
    - Foreign workers. Secret circular by Kaltenbrunner (RSD) demanding frequent police raids (#363)
    - Himmler's detention and interrogation methods (#364)
    - Forerunners of Wehrwolfs (#365)
    - The mentality of the 20 July conspirators (#366)
    - Himmler - Chief executioner (#367)
    - Hitler put Himmler in charge of Allied POWs and internees last October (#368)
    - Death sentences under the Heydrich regime (#369)
    - Black Market - New version (#370)
    - Officials and doctors to stay put (#371)
    - Scorched earth east of the Rhine. Letter quoting top secret order of Keitel that transport installations are not to be destroyed beyond repair (#372)
    - Himmler encourages denunciation of officers by men (#373)
    - German Propaganda needs Allied "War Criminals" - Keitel order (#374)
    - Prospect of Allied occupation. Extracts from letters by German civilians (#375)
    - "Deutsche Lufthansa" kept in readiness (#376)
    - The last round. Bormann decrees which show various aspects of Party's final struggle to maintain authority in face of moral and material disintegration (#377)
    - Recruits for the Master Race (#378)
    - Himmler's children (#379)
    - Small-bore rifles go to war (#380)
    - Model order demanding use of arms against German civilian defeatists (#381)
    - White flag versus Swastika (two copies) (#382) (Folder 3: 2)
    - Doves of Peace not welcome in Germany (#383)
    - The Catholic Church in Nazi Germany (#384)
    - Hitler mistrusted commanding generals (#385)
    - Eight extracts from soldiers' letters (#386)
    - Himmler orders death penalty for anyone in SS or Police who uses the Russian equivalent of the "son of a b---" curse. In Germany the mother is sacred (#387)
    - Model order re slack execution of orders and poor fighting discipline on the offensive (#388)
    - Right off the map! Germany acknowledges military defeat, but is ideologically on the offensive (#389)
    - Psychological warfare (#390)
    - "Protection" of Nazi youngsters (#391)
    - Stimmungsberichte (#392), 1943-1945
    - Change of uniforms (#393)
    - SS-children at any price (#394)
    - Kesselring's order of 3 April, introducing himself as new C-in-C West (#395)
    - Himmler vs. Bormann re court cases involving officers (#396)
    - Action Vlassov - Volunteers by force (#397)
    - They blamed the Party (#398)
    - Himmler was misunderstood. Clarification of his order re German women's duty to bear children out of wedlock (#399)
    - Nazi creed incompatible with Christian doctrine (#400)
    - Prick of Conscience? Re question whether the Party bears any guilt in this war, and countering soldiers' doubts as to justice of their cause (#401) (Folder 3: 3)
    - Slave labor (#402)
    - The Rundstedt gamble (#403)
    - Hess's star turns (#404)
    - Arrogance, treachery, incompetence, the verdict of Nazi leadership as defeat is at hand (#405)
    - Boys and girls against tanks (#406)
    - Nonfraternization in German-occupied Holland (#407)
    - Werewolves' pledge; two leaflets (#408)
    - Conscious of atrocities (#409)
    - "Mein Kampf" and German war guilt (#410)
    - Spontaneous anti-Semitism? (#411)
    - "If we perish, our enemies shall perish with us" (#412)
    - "Myth and Reality"; Nazi myth-building in defeat (#413)
    - Maltreatment of foreign workers (#414)
    - German comments on Goebbels' presentation of Hitler (#415)
    - Extracts from letters written by Fieldmarshal v. Rundstedt and members of his family (two copies) (#416)
    - The impact of war events and Nazi propaganda on the German People (#417)
    - Strong men in Nazi Germany: Todt and Speer (#418)
    - Twelve years' security service: A review by Himmler (#419)
    - Reactions to Nazi press, radio, and newsreels (#420) (Folder 3: 4)
    - OKW ordered concentration camp shootings of Allied POWs (#421)
    - Keitel kept in the dark? (#423)
    - Frau Heydrich's correspondence (#424)
    - Planned "spontaneous" demonstration of loyalty and affection to the Führer(#425)
    - Hitler's admission of defeat. Clash over the Führer succession question (#426)
    - How they looted. Göring - the art collector (#427)
    - Nazi propaganda methods (#428)
    - Looters' progress - Nazi exploitation of occupied territories (#429)
    - Hitler lectured Hindenburg on the "Jewish menace" (#430)
    - The importance of food production (#431)
    - Hitler's first cabinet meeting (#432)
    - Göring boasts about Luftwaffe successes. Leaves Sweden unmoved (#433)
    - "Schutz der Deutschen Frau im Einsatz!" (#434)
    - "Ministry for the No-Longer-Occupied Eastern Territories" (#435)
    - Foreign workers - Asset turned liability (#436)
    - Allied white-flag propaganda paralyzed German morale west of the Rhine (#437)
    - Food - The German people's war heritage: Dire shortage (#438)
    - The "Praetorian Guard" of Nazi Germany (#439)
    - He refused to join the Party; Letter of resignation from Eltz-Ruebenach (#440)
    - "Dr. Goebbels-Spende" - Propaganda for the Propaganda Minister (#441)
    - Concentration camps: "The Wehrmacht did not know" (#442)
    - Transcriptions of shorthand notes taken at Hitler's Hq. (#443) (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - The muzzled press of Nazi Germany (#445) (Folder 4: 2)
    - "A moment as favorable as that in 1939 would never recur." Hitler explains the timing of Germany's war (#446)
    - Forced marches of Allied officer POWs. Views on Vlassov and Germany's foreign legions. Hitler's brainwave - how to raise Russian scare in England (#447)
    - Hitler's scathing criticism of his foreign Divisions (#448)
    - - Hitler's reaction to the Duce's fall (#449), 1943
    - The decline of the Luftwaffe (#451) (Folder 4: 3)
    - Rumors by "Volksempfänger" (#452)
    - Gestapo and SD investigations of reports broadcast by "Sender Atlantik" (#453)
    - "Kill the Schweinhund." Nazi propaganda for Germans (#454)
    - Government and Party offices ignored Goebbels/Lammers appeal to help air raid victims (#455)
    - Himmler complains about getting Allied radio news instead of music (#456)
    - Nazis debated whether to hang Bishop of Münster for "treacherous utterances" (#457)
    - Listening to foreign broadcasts in wartime - a major problem in Nazi-Germany (#458)
    - Propaganda: Frick and Goebbels did not see eye to eye on issues of policy and authority (#459)
    - Confiscation of radio sets from Jews kept dark. Himmler raced Goebbels, and Hitler approved (#460)
    - Lammers out of favor with Hitler and Bormann (#461)
    - Japan in 1941 planned to attack Russia (#462)
    - Goebbels/Ribbentrop rivalry for control of Nazi Propaganda Agencies in foreign countries (#463)
    - "Operation Green" (Czechoslovakia): Germany's plan for aggression (#465)
    - Pre-Hitler government funds for Nazi Military Organizations (#467)
    - Nazi Black Lists of Jewish composers and orchestrators (#469)
    - correspondence between Cardinal Faulhaber, Archbishop of Munich, and Adolf Wagner, Gauleiter of Munich (#470), 1934
    - Membership in the NSDAP as the decisive factor in the appointment of high government officials (#475)
    - The background of Hitler's "Enabling Act," which suspended the Weimar Constitution (#480) (Folder 4: 4)
    - Dr. Schacht dismissed as President of Reichsbank (#482)
    - Göring's list of Nazi Party addresses (#483)
    - "Reich Chamber of Culture" blacklists of half-Jews and persons married to Jews (#487)
    - Nazi 1940 blueprint of the economic new order in postwar Europe (#488)
    - Comprehensive directive for police treatment of Berlin Jews (#489)
    - Nazi's "colonial" policies in occupied Eastern Territories (1941): Starvation and economic slavery (#491) (Folder 4: 5)
    - Nazi propaganda film against Allied bombing for showing in neutral countries vetoed by Goebbels (#492)
    - List of all German feature films produced from (#493), 1939-1944
    - Applications to Goebbels for permission to see films prohibited in Nazi Germany (#495)
    - Reich Propaganda Ministry blacklists of authors and journalists (pre-war) (#496)
    - After the fall of France - Hitler's opinion on political and military possibilities in Europe (#497)
  - NR-File (Folder 5: 1)
    - Report on German rearmament at the time of a disarmament conference, (#1), 1933
    - Report on juvenile delinquency, Munich, (#2), 1939-1945
    - Memorandum on special measures against juvenile delinquency during air raids, (#3), September 1943
    - Lists of Göring family presents for birthday and Christmas (#4)
    - Extracts from diary of Erich Pehrmann, NSFO Richtman, (#5), October 1944-February 1945
    - Extracts from diary of Oberleutnant Hauer, (#6), January-March 1945
    - Extracts from diary of Oberschuetze Anton Haas, (#7), September-October 1944
    - Reports by Eigrueber, Gauleiter of Vienna, on morale of troops and civilians (#8)
    - Keitel's order on provisions of Geneva Convention (#9)
    - Instruction not to publish works of Hungarian Communist Bela Bartok, (#10), May 1944
    - Letter by Speer to Brugmann - congratulation in connection with reception of award from Portuguese President General Carmona (#12)
    - Extracts from diary of Alfred Klonsk, Waffen-SS, formerly law student from Vienna, (#13), July-October 1944
    - Memorandum and order on deserters, (#14), November 1944
    - Memoranda on awards for destruction of tanks and planes (#15)
    - Memoranda on foreign workers (November 1944) and on Russians in German army (February 1945) (#16)
    - Memorandum on relations between German soldiers and civilians, (#17), November 1944
    - Memoranda on mistreatment of POWs (January 1945) and on military insignia (December 1944) (#18)
    - Memorandum on foreign workers, (#19), January 1945
    - Death sentences to German officers who failed to destroy bridge across the Rhine, (#20), March 1945
    - Letter written by Charlotte Kleeman to her family, (#21), April 1944
    - Letter written by Major Erich Franz to Melitta Franz, (#22), December 1944
    - Instruction what soldiers should write to their relatives, (#23), September 1944
    - Extracts from "Der politische Soldat" on functions of Sicherheitspolizei and Sicherheitsdienst, (#24), 1944
    - Order concerning desertions in Italy, (#25), May 1944
    - Memoranda concerning Allied interrogators, (#26), May 1944
    - Memoranda on educational value of detention units, (#27), April 1944
    - Telegram by Mackensen to soldiers of the 14th Army, (#28), May 1944
    - Memorandum on security issues, (#29)
    - Extract from "Panzerfunk" on the resistance to Allies in Germany, (#30), October 1944
    - Memoranda to SD Führer of Strassburg on morale and patriotism of Germans, (#31), November 1944
    - History of NSDAP, (#32), 1918-1939
    - Extracts from diaries of German soldiers, (#33), January-September 1944
    - Extracts from diary of Leutnant Horst Neujahr, (#34), 1941-1943
    - Extracts from diary of a German captain, no name, (#35), February-December 1942
    - Extracts from diary of a German soldier, no name, (#36), May-June 1944
    - Extracts from diary of Oberstabartz Kuentzell,; appeal signed by German officers Kuentzell and Mueller to German authorities to treat a group of F.F.I. members not as francs-tireurs but as regular POWs if the latter are taken as prisoners because these F.F.I. members had treated the German officers exceptionally well when the Germans were prisoners of these F.F.I. members (#37), September-October 1944
    - Report by SD of Strassburg on the structure of the Wehrmacht (#38)
    - Letter by R. Sautter, Protestant minister, to Margenthaller, Kultminister (#39)
    - NSDAP appeal to German youth, (#40), 1944
    - Memorandum on Catholic press in Germany, (#46), 1940
  - PID-File (Folder 5: 2)
    - Unnumbered
      - Two letters written by SS men regarding Oberst Stein's alleged complicity in Putsch of, 20 July 1944
      - Three reports concerning mass media in Germany
    - Numbered
      - List (Folder 5: 3)
      - Official obstacles to the activities of the church in July-August 1939 (#1) (), 1945 July 10 (Folder 5: 4)
      - SD agents to report on Catholic Church Festival (#2) (), 1945 July 11
      - Wealthy Jews to be branded as traitors and arrested by Gestapo (#3) (), 1945 July 11
      - SD report on corrupt conduct of Goebbels' protégé in Norway (#4) (), 1945 July 11
      - Discontentment amongst old fighters of the Party (#5) (), 1945 July 13
      - SD report on development of Czech radio (#5A) (), 1945 July 12
      - German penetration in South America in preparation for war (#5B) (), 1945 July 13
      - Air raids and propaganda (#6) (), 1945 July 13
      - Non-Aryan tuition means dismissal for civil servants (#7) (), 1945 July 16
      - Example of activities of German agent in South America (#8) (), 1945 July 17
      - Survey of air raid damages (#9) (), 1945 July 17
      - Göring suggests immediate shooting of captured Allied crews (#10) (), 1945 July 17
      - Illegal business transactions of Bremen Senator (#11) (), 1945 July 17
      - Dissolution of monasteries and confiscation of their property (#12) (), 1945 July 18
      - SD reports on the "Reicharundfunkgesellschaft" (#13) ()., 1945 July 19
      - Reactions to speeches by Hitler and Göring in (#14) (1945 July 19), April 1942
      - Church and Party: "A Christian cannot be a National Socialist" (#15) (), 1945 July 19
      - Nazi bosses buy castles while people worry about their future (#16) (), 1945 July 19
      - Hitler correspondence re offer to form new cabinet (#17) (), 1945 July 20
      - Indiscretions of high party members (#18) (), 1945 July 21
      - Story of birthday present for Germany's Postmaster-General (#19) (), 1945 July 22
      - Effect of Allied radio propaganda and German counter propaganda (#20) (), 1945 July 23
      - Policy concerning children of Eastern workers (#21) (), 1945 July 24
      - SD directives for the work of press specialists (#22) (), 1945 July 24
      - Protective custody and concentration camps (#23) (), 1945 July 25
      - Extracts from Hitlers' election speech in January 1933 (#24) (), 1945 July 30
      - Hitler letter outlining views on foreign policy (#25) (), 1945 July 30
      - Minutes on meeting at Hitler's HQ discussing transport problems (#26) (), 1945 August 1
      - Nazi Kreisleiter asks for churches as warehouses (#27) (), 1945 August 2
      - Letter concerning corruption of Gauleiter Hanke (#28) (), 1945 August 16
      - Letter by Bormann confirming cruel treatment of Germans fraternizing with foreigners (#29) (), 1945 August 18
      - Interrogation of Jodl, Rundstedt, Halder, Keitel (USSBS) (#30) () (missing), 1945 August 20
      - Ribbentrop's views on the future of a national Germany (#31) (), 1945 August 21
      - Interrogation report on Kesselring (USSBS) (#32) (), 1945 August 20
      - Bormann outlines position of the "Office of the Führer's Deputy" (#33) (), 1945 August 21
      - Schwerin von Krosigk's letter to Goebbels (#34) (), 1945 August 23
      - Bormanns' criticism of SD reports (#35) (), 1945 August 23
      - Göring takes care of Jewish property (#36) (), 1945 August 23
      - Hitler ordered killing of captured Commandos (#37) (), 1945 August 24
      - Report on the fighting capacity of the Russian army (#38) (), 1945 August 24
      - Doenitz thanks Guderian "in the name of coming generations" (#39) (), 1945 August 27
      - Schwerin-Krosigk: Report & Private Correspondence, 1938-1945 (#40) () (missing), 1945 August 27
      - Duplicates (#41) (missing)
      - Göring sanctioned Rosenberg's "booty staffs" (#42) (), 1945 August 31 (Folder 5: 5)
      - Seyss-Inquardt to Goebbels re "Bolshevistic black propaganda" to force Britain and UMA to adopt anti-Russian attitude, etc. (#43) (), 1945 July 5
      - Kortenhaus cables to Italy for sabotage groups and Werewolf activity (#44) (), 1945 July 8
      - Estimates on conscription of women; nobody dares rectify figures given to Goebbels (#45) (), 1945 July 8
      - Last stages of the "Axis" (#46) (), 1945 July 9
      - Pre-war morale in Gau Düsseldorf (#47) (), 1945 July 10
      - Bormann circular re Hitler's orders on scorched earth and evacuation (#48) (), 1945 July 11
      - Reactions to Hitler's policy in Poland and German-Russian agreement (#49) (), 1945 July 12
      - Best cure for absenteeism and Gestapo action (#50) (), 1945 July 16
      - Sects, religious societies, etc. to which civil servants can't belong (#51) (), 1945 July 16
      - SD report on Allied and German propaganda (#52) (), 1945 July 17
      - Goebbels propaganda directive of 5 February 1945 (#53) (), 1945 July 18
      - SD-Leipzig Report: Anti-Nazi activities, Nazi corruption (#54) (), 1945 July 19
      - Mundpropaganda (#55) (), 1945 July 19
      - Himmler's problems and their solution (#56) (), 1945 July 19
      - Copy of Communist propaganda leaflet in Hamburg camp after German capitulation, sent to OKW Staff by Chief of Gen. Staff (#57) (), 1945 July 20
      - Morale in German Army, February 1945 (#58) (), 1945 July 21
      - Existence of Communist opposition in Oanabrueck (#59) (), 1945 July 21
      - Troubles of Frieda Boehmker before fall of Bremen (#60) (), 1945 July 23
      - Wine and tobacco distributions before the fall of Bremen (#61) (), 1945 July 24
      - Popular views on Dr. Ley as reported by SD in 1943 (#62) (), 1945 July 24
      - Reactions to Dittmar broadcasts () (), end 1942-middle 1943 1945 July 25
      - Opposition activities in 1939 (#65) (), 1945 July 27
      - Morale reports: Kreis Munchen-Gladbach-Rheydt, (#66), January-August 1935
      - Reactions to rumors of impending war with Russia, May 1941 (#67) (), 1945 August 1
      - Schwerin-Krosigk: Reports and private correspondence, 1938-1945 (#68) (), 1945 September 1
      - Requisitioning of "Enemy of State" property in Austria by Nazis (#69) (), 1945 September 2
      - Duplicates (#70)
      - SD reports on general morale in Stuttgart area (August 1944) (#71) (), 1945 August 31
      - Duplicates (#72)
      - Japanese attempts to supplement Anti-Comintern Pact by military agreement (#73) (), 1945 September 4
      - I.G. Farben employee sent to Far East for SD work (#74) (), 1945 September 3